So today's דף *daf* is ט"ו *tet vav* and we start at
the משנה Mishna, *mishna* at the bottom of י"ד עמוד ב' *yud
daled amud bet*. So here's the משנה mishnah *mishna*, we have one
more of these cases of multiple sins with one act of sex
and then we're going to go on to broadening the discussion and
some interesting stories about it. So let's take a look though at
our משנה Mishnah? *mishna*. הבא על חמותו *Haba al chamoto*, a man
has sex with his mother-in-law, חייב chaiv עליה *chayav aleha*, so it's
possible, not obviously in every case, but it's possible to have the
following obligations all in this one act: משום חמותו *mishum chamoto*, his
mother-in-law, וכלתו *v'chalato*, his daughter-in-law. Now how could his mother-in-law also be
his daughter-in-law?
Well here, let's say
you have the guy here, so he is married to this
woman, I don't know, we'll call her רחל Rachel, *Rachel*, okay? And
that's her mother, I don't know what her mother is, anyway, we'll
call her mother שרה Sarah *Sarah*. So
that's his mother-in-law. How could his mother-in-law also be his daughter-in-law? Well
that's not so hard, right? He had a daughter and a granddaughter
and this granddaughter happens to be שרה Sarah, *Sarah*. So somebody marries
שרה Sarah *Sarah*, somebody marries his granddaughter, right, has a child, okay,
that would be his great-granddaughter.
So his great-granddaughter is only great-great-granddaughter, granddaughter,
oh granddaughter, then has
a daughter, yeah.
So his great-granddaughter is only forbidden to him rabbinically. So he marries
his great-granddaughter,
his mother-in-law is also his daughter is also his, did I get
that right? His mother-in-law, no no, I'm sorry, I'm getting it already
getting it mixed up. His mother-in-law is his daughter-in-law. Does that work?
I'm sorry, I'm getting it all already getting it mixed up.
His mother-in-law is his daughter-in-law.
I
got that
mixed up.
His daughter-in-law, yeah, so his mother-in-law is his son,
his son marries a woman, his son marries a woman, that's his
daughter-in-law, yeah, then they get divorced. Oh, that's not hard. Okay, his
son marries a woman, they get divorced, then this woman goes ahead
and has a child,
or whether they get divorced or not, this yeah, they
get divorced, that used to be his daughter-in-law, marries another man, they
have a child, and then he marries this.
So this woman is
his granddaughter,
his this
so his now mother-in-law, so he marries
רחל Rachel *Rachel*, no, if
he marries רחל Rachel *Rachel*, this woman W becomes his mother-in-law, רחל
Rachel *Rachel*'s mother, and then רחל *Rachel*'s mother used to be his
son's wife. Yes,
okay, so his mother-in-law is somebody that used to be married to
his son. Okay, this, now after this it gets easier. ואשת אחיו
*v'eshet achiv*, now this woman went ahead
and who's his wife's mother, also happens to have been a previous
his previous son's wife, and she goes ahead and she now marries
his brother. So now it's also his brother's wife. Then she gets
divorced from his brother, ואשת אחי אביו *v'eshet achi aviv*, and marries
his uncle. So now she's also that. ואחות אשתו *v'achot ishto*, it
also is his wife's sister. אוי *Oy*, how does it get to
be his wife's this woman gets I'm not even going to figure
that one out. Somehow this woman also gets to be his wife's
sister.
No, unless they have two daughters, what if רחל *Rachel* has a
sister?
But she this woman is his wife's
they both have the same father,
it has to be I think where the father did something wrong,
okay.
All right, we're not going to figure that one out. Let's keep
on moving. Okay, it also somehow happens to be his wife's sister,
ואשת איש *v'eshet ish*, and she's a married woman, ונדה *v'niddah*, fine.
וכן הבא על אם חמיו ועל אם חמותו *v'chen haba al em
chamiv v'al em chamoto*, even if you take out the word mother-in-law
and start the same thing but talking about his grandmother-in-law. So grandmother-in-law
is also a prohibition because the reason of mother-in-law is you can't
a man can't marry a woman and her mother or a woman
and her daughter and they also can't marry a woman and her
granddaughter. So you could have the same list if you took out
mother-in-law and put in grandmother-in-law, fine. רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan
ben Nuri אומר *Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri omer*, so okay, so that's
more or less along the lines of what we said before, we
didn't exactly figure out the sister case which would have been very
complicated, but we're going to move on. רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi
Yochanan ben Nuri אומר *Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri omer*, הבא על חמותו
חייב chaiv עליה משום חמותו ואם חמותו ואם חמיו *Haba al chamoto
chayav aleha mishum chamoto v'em chamoto v'em chamiv*. A man can have
sex with one woman and have transgressed three prohibitions: mother-in-law,
mother-in-law's mother, and mother-in-law's and
father-in-law's mother. אמרו לו amru lo, שלושה שמות shemot, אחד *Amru lo
shlosha sheimot echad*, they said no, in that case it would not
be three sin offerings since it's all about the sin of mother
and daughter or mother
and
daughter.
This
man is married to שרה, I don't
know,
רבקה Rivka and רחל, okay? Now, okay, this man is married to
these three different wives, alright? His, so this woman here, שרה's mother,
that's his mother-in-law, okay? That woman also is, that woman also, so
she had a child שרה, but she also was married to a
man who had a son whose, whose, רבקה Rivka was this woman,
שרה was this woman's daughter, רבקה Rivka was this woman's granddaughter, okay?
And also she had another child, a daughter, so this woman had
one daughter and two granddaughters. Got it? Right? One from a son
and one from a daughter, she had one daughter and two granddaughters.
He married all three of these women. He's allowed to, because he's
marrying a woman, her niece, and her other niece, right? And these
two are sisters, okay? They're cousins. You sort of see that case,
more or less? Now he has sex with this woman. So he's
having sex with his mother-in-law and his grandmother-in-law on, on two sides,
his, his mother-in-law's mother and his father-in-law's mother. Okay, so but the
whole sin is three sins of a woman and her daughter, a
woman and her granddaughter, a woman and her granddaughter. So it is
three, one act of sex, but because of the relations, that's the
easiest case, right? But anyway, it is those three sins. So רבי
יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri says three חטאות chatatot and
the rabbis say only one חטאת. chatat. Let's take a look at
the
גמרא. Gemara. אמר רבי אלעזר אמר רבי אושעיא, Amar Rabbi Elazar amar
Rabbi Oshaya, רבי יוחנן בן נורי וסומכוס אמרו דבר אחד. Rabbi Yochanan
ben Nuri veSumchus amru davar echad. So רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi
Yochanan ben Nuri that say three sin offerings in that case is
essentially saying the same as סומכוס Sumchus in another case. What is
it? רבי יוחנן בן נורי הד אמרין, Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri had
amrin, רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri what we just
said. סומכוס מאי? Sumchus mai? What סומכוס Sumchus said, we taught in
משנה, Mishnah, דף טז עמוד א. Daf Tes-Zayin Amud Aleph. שחטה את
בת בתה ואחר כך שחטה
את בתה. Shachata es bas bita ve'achar shachas es bita. So here's
another case of mother and daughter, except with animals. So somebody shechted
a mother sheep and then the granddaughter of that sheep and then
the daughter, the middle generation. So when he shechted, remember there's a
prohibition of shechting a mother and a child sheep on the same
day. So when you shecht the middle generation, generation, you did one
and three and then two, so two is the daughter of one
and the mother of three. So in the shechting of two, you
did two sins at the same time, a mother and daughter and
a daughter and a mother. Do you, do you see that? So
how many, how many lashes do you get? Is that one sin
or two sins?
The order doesn't really matter as long as you shecht all three
in the same day.
No, it does matter, because if you did one and then two,
that's one sin, and then you shechted three, that's another, that's sequential.
But because you did one and three, when you did one and
three you didn't do any sin, you shechted a mother and a
granddaughter, that's not a sin by shechting animals. And when you shecht
the middle in that one act of שחיטה shechita you did two
sins at the same time.
אותו ואת בנו לא תשחטו ביום אחד. Oso ve'es beno lo tishchatu
beyom echad. So no matter which order you do it in, you're
still doing it, a שור ושה shor ve'seh אותו ואת בנו. oso
ve'es beno.
Yes, but if you did them at separate times you obviously get
separate lashes. If you did it all in the same act, that's
the question, do you get separate lashes or not? Okay, so, so
it says סופג ארבעים, sofeg arba'im, you only get 40 lashes, it
was only one act of transgressing it in two ways, but it's
the same sin. סומכוס אומר משום רבי מאיר סופג שמונים. Sumchus omer
mishum Rabbi Meir sofeg shemonim. No, you get 40 lashes, two sets
of lashes. So you see they say the same thing, one act
but two variations of the same sin. So here too, one sleeping
with this woman and it's three variations of the same sin of
mother and daughter, of, but,
or mother and granddaughter, but it's three variations of the same sin.
So and you see if you say you get multiple lashes, it's
parallel to bringing multiple חטאות. chatatot. So they're essentially the same point.
Now of course you could distinguish that maybe there are different principles
that determine getting lashes from getting sin offerings, right? I mean, so
that's why you have מסכת כריתות Masechet Keritot and מסכת מכות, Masechet
Makkot, that how do you divide the sins and the acts might
be different in the two. But the גמרא Gemara divides them not
even by focusing on that difference, but by focusing on the nature
of the sin. So let's take a look. אמר רבא דילמא לא
היא, Amar Rava dilma lo hi, maybe it's not similar. עד כאן
לא קאמר Ad kan lo ka'amar רבי יוחנן בן נורי הכא, hacha,
when did רבי יוחנן בן נורי say that by sleeping with this
woman you get three sins, three sin offerings? אלא משום שמות מחולקים,
Ela mishum shemos muchlakim, that they are conceptually different sins.
דמיקריא חמותו, De'mikarya chamoso, ומיקריא אם חמותו, u'mikarya em chamoso, ומיקריא אם
חמיו, u'mikarya em chamiv, that this woman has essentially vis-a-vis him three
labels: mother-in-law,
mother-in-law's mother, father-in-law's mother. So that's three different, it's the same sin
of mother and daughter, mother and granddaughter, that's one פסוק. pasuk. But
at the end of the day, it's different because one is אשה
ובתה, isha u'bitah, the other is בת בתה, bas bitah, and the
other is בת בנו. bas beno. So they are given three different
labels, the, you know, this woman's relationship to him. And therefore it's
three sin offerings. אבל גבי אותו ואת בנו, Aval gabei oso ve'es
beno, ד... de... דכולהו אותו ואת בנו מקיים. d'khulu oto v'et beno
mikayim. The Torah doesn't say don't שחט shecht a mother and a
daughter, don't שחט shecht a daughter and a mother. It doesn't label
it differently, it only has one label, אותו ואת בנו. oto v'et
beno. So you did two אותו ואת בנוs, oto v'et beno but
in this other case you did three different things: אשה ובתה, isha
u-bitah, בת בתה, bat bitah, בת בנה. bat binah. The Torah explicitly
labels them differently. So maybe here you get three, but there you
would only get one. Okay, דאין
שמות מחולקין, d'ein shemot m'chulakin, that they're not distinct, they're not given
distinct labels. לא, lo, he would not say it. אמר רב נחמן
בר יצחק, amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, so that's how come just
Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri that says three separate sins in our Mishnah
would not agree in the case of the sheep, because there it
only has one label. Now the Gemara is going to distinguish it
the other way. אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק, amar Rav Nachman bar
Yitzchak, עד כאן לא קאמר סומכוס, ad kan lo ka'amar Sumchus, and
not only that, maybe Sumchus doesn't agree to Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri.
When does he say by the case of the sheep that it's
two different sins, two different
lashes? אלא גבי אותו ואת בנו, ela gabei oto v'et beno, דגופין
מחולקין, d'gufin m'chulakin, only by this where it's different bodies. What does
it mean different bodies? There's the grandmother and there's the granddaughter, and
so each one, meaning what defines this generation two as problematic is
two different things defined as problematic. One is the sheep's mother and
the other is the sheep's daughter. Okay, דגופין מחולקין, d'gufin m'chulakin, אבל
הכא דאין גופין מחולקין, aval hacha d'ein gufin m'chulakin, אימא כרבי אבא
אמר רב יוחנן סבירא ליה. eima k'Rabbi Abba amar Rav Yochanan sevira
lei. Here it's not different bodies, maybe he says it's all one.
Now the question is, what do you mean it's not different bodies?
The same way when you have generations of sheep, right, and then
you
shecht this, this is defined because of this it's defined as a
daughter and because of this it's defined as a mother, right, that's
the sheep case, yes, right, you got that case? So here too,
she's defined because of Sarah she's defined as a mother-in-law, because of
Rivka she's defined as a grandmother-in-law on the son's side, because of
Rachel she's defined as a grandmother-in-law on the daughter's side. So it's
also three different people make give her her designation, the same way
here two different sheep give the middle one its designation. So why
is it different?
Why would this be all kind of like genericide?
No, because we're trying to say there you get two different, there
Sumchus says you get two sets and here you would say only
one. So why would you say here would be fewer? Here there's
much more of a compelling reason to say that you bring multiple
sin offerings. So the Gemara says, finishes it up, דאמר רבי אבא
אמר רב יוחנן, d'amar Rabbi Abba amar Rav Yochanan, and here's the
real key, because Rabbi Abba says in the name of Rabbi Yochanan,
it says at the end of the pasuk about sleeping with a
mother and her daughter or granddaughter, שארה הנה זמה היא. she'erah henah
zimah hi.
It is the same flesh, it is a fornication, or some word
זמה zimah means something like that, anyway it is forbidden sex. הכתוב
עשאן לכולן זמה אחת. hakatuv asaan l'khulan zimah achat. In the end,
it ends with זמה היא zimah hi in the singular. So in
the end the pasuk here is saying this is all the same
sin. That's the pasuk at the end of mother and daughter, mother
and granddaughter. So that's saying it's all the same sin, whereas here
by the sheep it would be different sins. You don't have a
pasuk that basically says it's all one. Okay, but anyway, although the
Gemara did try to say the sheep case is more of all
one, is more of distinct, what more is compelling I think is
to see this case as distinct because not only are there different
people that give her that designation, but also it is given different
labels: אשה ובתה, isha u-bitah, בת בתה, bat bitah, בת בנה, bat
binah, different labels. Okay, so that is the end of, or at
least the temporary end, we will revisit in a little bit, of
this issue of
these very complex cases of multiple relations, and some of them require,
we didn't even unpack them fully, some of them require, you know,
doing whole charts to figure out how you got a woman to
be both. Let's take a look now at the next Mishnah, we
have a little bit of a story.
Okay, so אמר רבי עקיבא, amar Rabbi Akiva, said Rabbi Akiva, שאלתי
את רבן גמליאל ואת רבי יהושע, sha'alti et Rabban Gamliel v'et Rabbi
Yehoshua, I asked Rabban Gamliel and Rabbi Yehoshua, באטליז של אמוס, b'itliz
shel Amos, in the meat market, you might remember אטליז itliz sometimes
pronounced written with a zayin, אטליז, itliz, when it talks about selling
a בכור bechor in an אטליז, itliz, בכור bechor with a מום,
mum, in the meat market of Emmaus, wherever it is, שהלכו ליקח
בהמה למשתה בנו של רבן גמליאל. shehalchu likach behemah l'mishteh b'no shel
Rabban Gamliel. There you see it's a meat market because they were
going to buy an animal, they were going to buy some meat
because it was Rabban Gamliel's
son's משתה, mishteh, which probably means it was his wedding party. Okay,
so his son was getting married. And so here's what we were
discussing while we were doing things. הבא על אחותו ועל אחות אביו,
haba al achoto v'al achot aviv,
so this is what they're talking about when they're in the middle
of the meat market, maybe they're thinking about this because they're thinking
about getting
married, his son's wedding. Yeah, Rabban Gamliel was there, this was, well
you know, wedding, sex, they were thinking about. Now of course, you
know, what do they do, why is it telling us in this
context? So if you look at Tosafot, not the Tosafot that's printed
up in the upper left, this little Tosafot underneath the Rashi, which
says שהלכו ליקח בהמה למשתה, shehalchu likach behemah l'mishteh, why is it
giving us this story? So it says להודיע שבחן, l'hodia shivchan, to
tell you how great these rabbis were, שאף על פי שהיו טרודים,
she'af al pi shehayu trudim, even though they were distracted, right, they
were doing a shopping trip, היו עוסקים בדברי תורה, hayu oskim b'divrei
Torah, they were still talking Torah. Right, so but you know, to
me I think it's along the lines that I sort of said
the other day, which is although, you know, that there's something... A
little bit like a mind game about some of this type of
a stuff, about like how we, how can you get somebody that
has all of these designations. Although we'll see that the question was
not can we figure out how a woman can have five designations,
the question really is going to be about the directly about the
הלכה, halacha, how many times do you bring one חטאת chatat or
do you bring multiple חטאות. chataot. But yes, you can imagine
these cases happened to her.
No, but you know, it's obviously it's still theoretical conversation, but it's
not necessarily a mind game. Can you figure out how many times
you can make a woman אסור? asur? You know, but yes, it
is. So let's take a look. So here's the question that was
asked. הבא על אחותו ועל אחות אביו ועל אחות אמו. haba al
achoto veal achot aviv veal achot imo.
Somebody has sex with a woman that is both his sister and
his father's sister and his mother's sister. You might realize this is
a little hard for somebody to be both your sister and a
person's sister and his father's sister. So the גמרא Gemara is going
to describe how that could happen. But here was the question that
was asked, not how can you figure out how that could happen,
but מהו. mahu. Now we really get to the heart of it,
which is how do you define whether there are multiple sin offerings
or not multiple sin offerings? We already had a hint before about
right the case about mother and daughter and granddaughter, are they defined
as distinct sins or not distinct sins? So here you have a
case about sister and father's sister and mother's sister. What's the story?
חייב אחת על כולן, chayav achat al kulan, is it one sin
offering because it's one act? או חייב על כל אחת ואחת, o
chayav al kol achat veachat, or multiple sin offerings? So here basically
they're asking what was implicit in all the previous משניות. mishnayot. In
all the previous משניות mishnayot was implicit that if it's different designations
and different sins, even if it's the same act, you bring multiple
sin offerings. Here רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva was saying that they were
trying to that this was when they were trying to initially figure
that out. If it's one act and multiple sins, multiple different עריות,
arayot, is it one sin offering or multiple? That was his question
for them. You know, the גמרא Gemara often does that, that it
sort of tells you a more complicated case and then gets to
the more basic. But conceptually, this משנה Mishnah, really was the foundation
of the previous ones, that it's one multiple things, one sin offering
or multiple. אמרו לו, amru lo, they said to him, לא שמענו,
lo shamanu, we don't have a tradition about that. אבל שמענו aval
shamanu what we do have a tradition is, הבא על ה' נשים
ובהעלם אחת שהוא חייב על כל אחת ואחת. haba al chamesh nashim
uvehelem achat shehu chayav al kol achat veachat. Let's say נדה, niddah,
right, it probably should be ה' נשים נדה. chamesh nashim niddah. So
let's say a man had five had there were five
different women involved, not one woman and multiple designations, but multiple women
and one designation. All of his wives, he had five wives, they
were all in נדה, niddah, and he had sex with each one
of them and he had forgotten that they were נדה, niddah, or
forgotten it was prohibited, whatever. So therefore it's the same sin but
with multiple different persons. That we know that you bring multiple sin
offerings. And it says ורואים אנו שהדברים קל וחומר. veroyim anu shehadevarim
kal vachomer. It would seem to us that it's a קל וחומר.
kal vachomer. If for the same sin you bring multiple sin offerings
if done with different people, then even if right you understand how
these are mirror images, right? The same sin with multiple people, one
person multiple sins. So it would seem to us that if it's
the same sin you bring multiple sin offerings with multiple people, one
person multiple sins is even more of a reason to define it
as multiple sin offerings because they're distinct sins even though it's one
act. Okay, so that's really the question. What distinguishes and the way
the גמרא Gemara phrases this and we've seen this designation before is
שמות מחולקים, shemot mecholakim, do names, meaning labels, distinct sins, we've had
that phrase before, שמות, are they distinct sins? Does that mean distinct
sin offerings? Or is it גופי מחולקים, gufi mecholakim, different bodies, different
acts, different people involved in the act, is that what distinguishes it
as different sin offerings? So they said we have a tradition about
גופי מחולקים, gufi mecholakim, presumably it's a קל וחומר kal vachomer that
שמות מחולקים shemot mecholakim also means distinct sin offerings. Let's take a
look at the גמרא. Gemara. היכי דמי, heichi dami, what's the case?
First of all, how do you get this crazy case that a
woman is both his sister and his father's sister and his mother's
sister? So it first assumes that it means it was three different
women. So אילימא כדקתני, eileima kidekatani, like it sounds like three different
women, מאי תיבעי ליה, mai tibei lei, then what type of a
question is that? Obviously it's three sin offerings. הרי שמות מחולקים הרי
גופי מחולקים. harei shemot mecholakim harei gufi mecholakim. It's both different sins
and different people. אלא הכי קתני. ela hachi katani. No, it's not
three different women. Here's what it says. הבא על אחותו שהיא אחות
אביו שהיא אחות אמו. haba al achoto shehi achot aviv shehi achot
imo. One woman who is both his sister, his mother's sister, and
his father's sister. חייב אחת על כולן או חייב על כל אחת
ואחת. chayav achat al kulan o chayav al kol achat veachat. So
it's one person, three designations. Is it one sin offering or multiple
sin offerings? מהו, mahu, what do we say? מי אמרינן הרי שמות
מחולקים, mi amrinan harei shemot mecholakim, do you say it's different sins,
different designations, so it's three sin offerings? או דילמא הרי אין גופי
מחולקים, o dilma harei ein gufi mecholakim, on the other hand, it's
not different bodies, it's one person. So is that enough to say
different sin offerings? As we learned from all the previous משניות, mishnayot,
the answer is yes, different designation is enough. But here they're asking
that even with one person and one act, but here they're asking
that question. אמרו לו, and they said back to him, לא שמענו,
lo shamanu, we don't know about that. אבל שמענו הבא על ה'
נשים נדות ובהעלם אחת שהוא חייב על כל אחת ואחת. aval shamanu
haba al chamesh nashim niddot uvehelem achat shehu chayav al kol achat
veachat. We know, we do have a tradition that if it's his
five wives who are all נדות, niddot, it's one sin and multiple
women, that it's multiple sin offerings משום נדה, mishum niddah, it's all
the same designation. It's a lot more conversational. What's the story when
it's five women that it's all the same sin but you're חייב
chayav on each one because they're different people? אחותו שהיא אחות אביו
שהיא אחות אמו, Achoso she'hi achos aviv she'hi achos imo, this woman
who's both his sister, father's sister, and mother's sister, שהן ג' שמות,
she'hein gimmel shemos, that it's different types of labels, אינו דין שחייב
על כל אחת ואחת? eino din she'chaiv al kol achas v'achas? How
much more so should you be חייב chayav, on each one? Now
of course, you know, the whole that whole קל וחומר kal v'chomer
has hidden in it an assumption which is exactly the question: what's
worse, different people, different acts, or different sins? And they say, so
they say, well we're going to assume that different sins is more
of a reason for bringing multiple sin offerings than different acts, so
we'll make a קל וחומר. kal v'chomer. But of course that assumption
is exactly what could be questioned. And that's what the response is.
So the גמרא Gemara says איכא למפרך, ika l'mifrach, you can challenge
that קל וחומר. kal v'chomer. מה להני נדות שכן גופים מוחלקין? Mah
l'hanei niddos she'kein gufim m'chulakin? You know, so maybe the case of
five of five wives is worse because it's different people. So what?
Five different acts. Five different acts, exactly, with five different people. It's
not only five different acts with the same person multiple times. It's
five different acts with five different people. So, you know, so how
can you make a קל וחומר? kal v'chomer? Then that's exactly the
question: what makes it, what is worse? So the גמרא Gemara says
אלא אמר קרא, ela amar kra, rather the verse says ערבת אחותו
גילה. ervas achoso gilah. Remember we had a while ago why did
the, you know, why was it כתוב כרת באחותו, kasuv kares b'achoso,
that by אחותו achoso the תורה Torah is a little redundant about
the fact that you get כרת? kares? And the basic answer was
לחייב על כל אחת ואחת, l'chaiv al kol achas v'achas, to tell
you exactly this point, that for every separate designation is a separate
sin offering, every separate שם, sheim, even if it's only one body
and one act. So here at the end we're not learning it
out from your קל וחומר, kal v'chomer, we're learning it out from
a פסוק. pasuk. לחייב על אחותו שהיא אחות אביו שהיא אחות אמו,
L'chaiv al achoso she'hi achos aviv she'hi achos imo, to tell you
that you will get, if you have a case of a sister
who's also father's sister and mother's sister, you get it for every
designation. So in the end you can't learn it out from a
קל וחומר, kal v'chomer, from a פסוק pasuk though, because that sin
is extra, we can learn the idea. So now we have the
principle that both גופים מוחלקין, gufim m'chulakin, different bodies, are different sin
offerings, and שמות מוחלקין, shemos m'chulakin, different labels, different prohibitions, even with
the same person, even in the same act. The one case you
would not bring different sin offerings is the same sin with the
same person multiple times. So if a man and wife have sex
when she's a נדה, niddah, she forgot that she was a נדה,
niddah, and they do that multiple times, then as long as they
don't remember in between, that's another thing that divides, right? ידיעות מחלקות,
Yedios m'chulakos, becoming aware divides. But as long as they don't become
aware in between, they have sex multiple times, then each of them
only brings one sin offering, not multiple. But if either of those
becomes, either you remember in between, or it is different women, you
know, different, different people are involved, or it is different designations, so
there's one person who has multiple designations, all of those are reasons
to bring multiple sin offerings. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara is
just going to try to figure out how you get this case
of a sister who is father's sister and mother's sister. So, אמר
רב אדא בר אהבה, Amar Rav Adda bar Ahava, משכחת לה, mashkachas
lah, and here's how you can get this case, you can find
it ברשיעא בר רשיעא, b'rashia bar rashia, in somebody who's a wicked
person the son of a wicked person, that they're doing a lot
of prohibitions. What's the case? שבא על אמו והוליד ב' בנות. She'ba
al imo v'holid shtei banos. A man has sex with his mother
and now has two daughters. וחזר ובא על אחת מהן, V'chozar u'ba
al achas meihen, and then he has sex with his daughter, okay,
so wicked acts throughout here. והוליד בן, V'holid ben, and from one
of his daughters who's also, right, if this daughter was the daughter
of his mother, this daughter of his that he's having sex with
is also his sister. You got it? So he's having sex now
with a woman who is both his daughter and his sister. Okay,
והוליד בן, v'holid ben, and now from that
you have a son. Now we're not done yet. Okay, so let
me, let me draw this case. This is a good thing. What?
How is that his sister? How is she his sister? Because he
had sex with his mother. Oh, he had sex with his mother.
Okay. So, all right. So here is, it's interesting he's only called
רשע rasha the one who had sex with the mother, not the
before we had sex with the daughter, it wasn't. Yeah, I mean,
I don't think the mother was saying there it's not a רשע,
rasha, but here because it's underscoring, it's underscoring how many multiple sins
that he did, so it's using that בר רשיעא.
bar rashia. Okay. We'll do this, we'll try to use the letters
here for generations. I don't know if that works. Anyway.
So anyway, well let's just, or let's just do it one more
time. I can try to explain. Okay. Anyway. So here's a man.
Yeah, we'll call him whatever, we'll call him X.
He has sex with his mother. Okay. He has two daughters.
Rachel and Leah. But they could have him having sex with a
man also while they're at it. You won't get kids out of
that.
You have to get relationships. Yes, but we're trying to get a
woman that has multiple. So you're not going to get kids out
of... In order to have offspring with multiple designations, you need to
have sex with a woman. Okay, so he has to have רחל
לאה. Leah. These are both sisters. These are those sisters. Yes, those
sisters. Sisters and daughters. רחל לאה. Leah. Now he has sex with
רחל and has a son called I don't know ראובן. Reuven. Okay
now so ראובן Reuven is now his what? Grandson but no his
son. But son and grandson. Son what? No it's his son oh
you're right it's not his grandson. Well his son whatever we're not
going to worry about that. Now what does ראובן Reuven do? Now
what does ראובן Reuven do? Okay. So he has a so wait
a minute. רישא בר רישא... Risha bar risha... wait a minute where
am I? He's the son he's the son of his daughter. Shhh.
וחזר בעל אכמן והוליד בן ובא בנו על אחות אמו שהיא אחותו
שהיא אחות אביו. Vechazar ba'al achman veholid ben uva beno al achot
imo shehi achoto shehi achot aviv. Okay fine. So he now has
sex with his mother's לאה. Leah. He has sex with לאה. Leah.
Who is לאה? Leah? It's his mother's sister right because they have
the same mother right? אחות אמו. achot imo. His
father's sister right because they also have the same mother right? And
it is his sister because it's his father's daughter. So now he's
having sex with לאה Leah and his mother's sister, his father's sister,
and his sister.
And his father's sister. And yeah and his mother's sister,
father's sister, and his sister. Okay? So that's how you get a
woman that's רישא בר רישא risha bar risha because this person first
has sex with his mother and then
has sex
with his daughter sister right? And then this guy is a רשע
בר רשע rasha bar rasha because this guy after his father did
those things he went and he had sex with לאה Leah which
is all of those multiple...
Is it separate sins if it's daughter of mother and daughter of
father?
No well yeah but we're talking about sister of mother sister of
father.
Right not daughter of mother daughter of father.
Right but it's also the daughter of his mother and daughter of
his father.
I
yeah but that's not but that's all in the same person. So
it's a woman who is daugh... yes that's not separate. Okay that's
one that's one designation. Okay so now there we go. All right.
דהוי ליה רישא בר רישא Dehavilei risha bar risha so this is
a wicked person descendant of a wicked person. Now. תנו רבנן Tano
rabanan fine but we've laid the principle that you are חייב chayav
for not only גופים מחולקים gufim m'chulakim but also שמות מחולקים. shemot
m'chulakim. בעל וחזר בעל וחזר בעל חייב על כל אחת ואחת דברי
רבי
אליעזר. Ba'alav vechazar ba'alav vechazar ba'alav chayav al kol achat ve'achat divrei
rabbi eliezer.
Now we actually are going to get to what I said is
only one קרבן korban but now we are going and we've assumed
that until now but now we're going to see that that actually
is an issue of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and the חכמים. Chachamim.
The same sin with the same person multiple times. So imagine again
a husband and wife they she forgets she's a נדה nidda he
forgets he's a נדה nidda they have sex multiple times. בעל וחזר
בעל וחזר בעל. Ba'alav vechazar ba'alav vechazar ba'alav.
Same sin same person multiple times without remembering in between. Okay so
we as we assumed that that is only one קרבן. korban. You
need to either be different people or different sins. Not the same
person multiple times but here רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer saying no the
fact that it's different acts that's enough for different קרבנות korbanot דברי
רבי אליעזר. divrei rabbi eliezer. וחכמים אומרים Vechachamim omrim and חכמים chachamim
say and this is how we rule אינו חייב אלא אחת. eino
chayav ela achat. No if it's same person same sin even if
it's multiple times one sin offering. ומודים לרבי אליעזר Umodim l'rabbi eliezer
but they do agree בבא על חמש נדות בבת אחת שהוא חייב
על כל אחת ואחת b'ba al hamesh niddot b'vat achat shehu chayav
al kol achat ve'achat that if it is five even if it's
the same sin of being a נדה nidda if it is different
persons גופים מחולקים gufim m'chulakim then it is different sin offerings like
we said before. הואיל והוא גרם להם Ho'il vehu garam lahem since
he caused them. Now what does that mean הוא גרם להם? hu
garam lahem? It means that now we are thinking that the reason
is not גופים מחולקים. gufim m'chulakim. גופים מחולקים Gufim m'chulakim on itself
would not be a reason to bring multiple sin offerings. The reason
is here רבקה Rivka now finally we're looking at it from the
woman's perspective all this had been the man's perspective because with he
if he had sex with his five wives and they were נדות
niddas and they also forgot that they were נדות niddas how many
sin offerings are going to be brought on the woman's end? Each
woman will bring one sin offering so he is going to have
caused five sin offerings to be brought by his wives okay because
he had sex with them I mean he's causing their קרבן korban
but as a result of the action the women are each bringing
a different sin offering for each woman he sleeps with right? So
therefore for him too you can't say oh it's all one big
sin he too would have to bring a different sin offering for
each case. Okay so meaning in principle we would not say גופים
מחולקים gufim m'chulakim the reason here at least it's phrased here that
he brings multiple sin offerings is because each of the women he's
sleeping with brings a sin offering so he can't be they bring
a sin offering and he doesn't.
What's the difference between גופים... gufim...
Because let's say for example they were, let's say they were אנוס,
onus, or let's say it wasn't a person, let's say it's a
גופים מוחלקים Gufim Mochlakim in inanimate objects or something like that. Okay?
So, but because they're bringing sin offerings, he's bringing as well for
each act. So the Gemara is going to challenge that. אמר רבא
לרב נחמן, Amar Rava le-Rav Nachman, מי
אמרינן חוב הוא גרם להם? mi amrinan hov hu garam lahem? Is
that really the reason why he brings when it's multiple women, because
he caused them to bring multiple ones? ותניא, ve-tanya, let's say we
have a case where there's a—it's not parallel. הוא בהעלם אחת והיא
בהעלמות. Hu be-he'elam achat ve-hi be-he'elamot. Let's say he had sex with
his wife five times and he forgot consistently that she was a
נדה. niddah. She, in between each act of sex, remembered she was
a נדה niddah and she forgot. So remember, when you remember in
between and then forget again, it divides the acts. So how many
sin offerings would she bring if she remembered, forgot, remembered, forgot? Five.
How many would he bring? One, because he had only—he never remembered
in between. Okay? הוא אינו חייב אלא אחת, Hu eino chayav ela
achat, he only brings one, והיא חייבת על כל אחת ואחת, ve-hi
chayavet al kol achat ve-achat, and she brings for each act. So,
and if you said that there's a principle that every time she
brings a different קרבן, korban, he brings, then he should have to
bring five times because she brought five times. So you see you
don't say that just because one of the parties brings a קרבן,
korban, the other one has to—it divides the act for the other
one. You could also reverse it. He could have remembered in between
and she could have not. But the point is you judge each
party separately. You don't say how it's defined for one party determines
how it's defined for the other. אלא אימא, Ella eima, so you're
right, it's not because you go by what she did to define
what he did, but rather it's the reason we've been saying before,
הוי גופים מוחלקים, hovei gufim mocholakim, because it is different people involved
in each time, forget whether they bring multiple קרבנות korbanot or not
multiple קרבנות, korbanot, that is enough to say that he—that it's a
different act and brings multiple times. So now we go back to
the principle: what defines it as different acts for קרבנות? korbanot? Different
people are involved, or you—or a different labels, different sins, or you
remember in between. Those are sufficient. But the same person, same sin,
multiple times, only one sin offering. Yeah?
Is there a difference between whether you forget that נדה niddah is
prohibited or if you forget that you're in the—no, no.
Those are the same. The two classic examples of שוגג shogeg is
you forget that it's prohibited or you forget that
it's—you forget the law, you forget the facts. Okay. So let's take
a look now at the Gemara.
Okay. Now we thankfully turn away from cases of sex and turn
to other areas. שבת. Shabbos. Okay, so let's take a look. איבעיא
להו, Iba'ya lehu, they raised the following question.
Did I skip a line? Okay. איבעיא להו. Iba'ya lehu. קצר וקצר
מאי למימר רבי אליעזר? Katzar ve-katzar mai le-amar Rabbi Eliezer?
What would רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer say, who says that multiple acts
is—is multiple sin offerings, if it was another example of multiple acts
not to do with sex? Let's say on שבת. Shabbos. You went
ahead and you plucked an apple, you forgot that it was שבת,
Shabbos, and then an hour later you picked another apple. Same sin,
multiple times, multiple acts. Would he say two sin offerings or one?
So you would think two, just like the case before about having
sex twice. Let's see what the Gemara's questioning. קצר וקצר מאי למימר
רבי אליעזר, Katzar ve-katzar mai le-amar Rabbi Eliezer, excuse me, מאי למימר
רבי אליעזר. mai le-amar Rabbi Eliezer. טעמא דרבי אליעזר התם משום דהוה
תרתי? Ta'ama de-Rabbi Eliezer hatam mishum de-hava tartei? Is the reason
for רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer of two sin offerings because you did—you
did two things, you did it twice, אמטו להכי אמר חייב, amtu
le-hachi amar chayav, and because of that he says you're חייב, chayav,
על כל אחת ואחת, al kol achat ve-achat, for each one,
and as a result of that, okay, והכא נמי דעביד
תרתי, ve-hacha nami de-avid tartei, here too you did two. It's just
a simple point, you did two acts, you bring two sin offerings.
So no חכמה, chochma, and therefore by שבת Shabbos as well. או
דילמא, O dilma, no, there's a reason there that he says they're
distinct. דילמא טעמא דרבי אליעזר התם משום דאי אפשר לו לערבן ביאה
זו בזו. Dilma ta'ama de-Rabbi Eliezer hatam mishum de-i efshar lo le-arvan
bi'ah zo be-zo. It's impossible to have two acts of sex simultaneously.
You can't conceptually say that it was one act. אמטו להכי אמר
רבי אליעזר חייב על כל אחת ואחת. amtu le-hachi amar Rabbi Eliezer
chayav al kol achat ve-achat.
Therefore he says you bring a קרבן korban in each one, they're
separate acts. The contrast will be obvious. אבל קצר כגרוגרת וקצר כגרוגרת,
Aval katzar ke-grogoret ve-katzar ke-grogoret,
if you, you know, cut something growing off of a tree and
it was the size of a גרוגרת, grogoret, like a pressed date,
which is the minimum size, and then you did it again, בהעלם
אחת, be-he'elam achat, in one forgetfulness, כיון דאפשר לו לערבי שתי גרוגרות
בבת אחת, kivan de-efshar lo le-arvei shtei grogorot be-vat achat, in theory
you could have picked that quantity all at once, right? So therefore,
if you say that, אינו חייב אלא אחת, eino chayav ela achat,
maybe only bring one. Which means the following, let me just reframe
it, okay? I think I've said this before. When you say there's
a minimum—think about eating. The minimum size for eating something is a
כזית. kezayit. When I eat a big loaf of bread, did I
do five acts of eating because it was five כזיתים? kezayitim? Or
no, it was one act of eating. כזית kezayit is just a
minimum. It doesn't mean that for every כזית kezayit we define it
as a separate act, right? It's still one act since it had
a minimum size. Okay. Now, you could say that by a lot
of things. So if I pick three apples off of a tree,
did I do three separate acts of picking, right? Let's say I
picked them all with one hand at one time. Three separate acts
of picking? Or was it one act of picking and it was
because it had a minimum size in it? Okay. So you would
be inclined to say if it was all at the same time,
it was one act of picking that had a minimum size. Like
nobody would ever say that if I picked an apple, because an
apple has multiple גרוגרות, grogerot, I'd bring multiple קרבנות. korbanot. That clearly
was one act. Okay, it just had a minimum size.
I
know, but now let's say I picked the apples at three distinct
times. So that does make it to some degree different acts, but
in theory I can view it as one big picking of apples,
and maybe therefore it's only one sin offering. But I could not,
so that's maybe in that case it is only one. רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer says multiple by sex acts. Because sex acts, there's no
way you could have done separate sex acts at the same time,
right? You could have multiple apples in your one picking, but you
cannot have multiple sex acts in the same, in the exact same
act. So there's no way conceptually you can define it as one
act. And therefore he says two sin offerings. But when it's other
types of things that in theory you could have all done it
at the same time, that therefore you could define as one act.
So do you have a
limit, how much you could... Right, let's say it was 100 apples,
there's no way you could pick it at, I don't know, it's
an interesting question.
So if a man is sleeping with a woman, yes, and they
have sex multiple times, each one of those times is a separate
act, even though they were sleeping together only once.
Well,
yes, that's right. Meaning,
you know, the, what's not being spelled out here, what the גמרא
Gemara definitely does say in cases of חיוב, chiyuv, like if it's
intentional, is if they never actually, if he never actually fully withdraws,
but they continue having sex, right, the גמרא Gemara actually says that
that's continued to be חייב chayav for the continuous sex even though
there was not a full withdrawal. What exactly here considers to be
a separate act of sex is not being, you know, for the
חיוב חטאת chiyuv chatas is not being fully spelled out. That is
true. But whatever, but whatever we define as separate, it can't all
happen at the same moment. It can all happen in the same
process, but not at the same moment. Okay, whereas the plucking of
one apple or ten apples could be, I just cut off the
branch, I could do it all in one act.
Okay, so you're saying that if I pick something less than the
size of a גרוגרת, grogeret, you're never חייב, chayav even if I
pick, like, you know, in some...
Well, that's a question about what, no, about how do you combine
חצי שיעורים chatzi shiurim and what שיעור shiur you need to combine
חצי שיעורים. chatzi shiurim. Okay, but let's go on. Anyway, the גמרא
Gemara says like this. So what is the reason of רבי אליעזר?
Rabbi Eliezer? Is it everything that's a separate act or only when
conceptually there's no way you could combine it in one act? So,
so
what does the גמרא Gemara say? מאי. Mai. So what's the הלכה?
halacha? אמר רבא טעמא דרבי אליעזר התם משום דעביד תרתי הכא נמי
דעביד תרתי. Amar Rava ta'ama d'Rabbi Eliezer hatam mishum d'avid tartei hacha
nami d'avid tartei. So without any textual evidence, he just says, no,
I understand
רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, separate acts, even if in theory you could
combine them. רב יוסף אמר, Rav Yosef amar, and רב יוסף Rav
Yosef takes the other side of the debate. טעמא דרבי אליעזר התם
דאי אפשר לערבן. Ta'ama d'Rabbi Eliezer hatam d'i efshar l'arvan. No, the
only reason he says it is by sex, where there's no way
it could all have been done in one act. אבל
אפשר לערבן, Aval efshar l'arvan, if in theory you could have done
those multiple things in one act and it's again the same thing,
so אינו חייב אלא אחת. eino chayav ela achas. That he would
consider to be one act and only one sin offering. Okay, איתיבי,
eitvei,
so they're taking sides. איתיבי אביי לרבא. Eitvei Abaye l'Rava. רבא Rava
asked, אביי Abaye asked a question to רבא, Rava, who said that
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer would not distinguish. רבי אליעזר מחייב על תולדות
מלאכות במקום אבות מלאכות. Rabbi Eliezer mechayev al toldot melachot bimkom avot
melachot. So there's a general interesting position of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
by שבת, Shabbat, which is he says, how do you define separate
עבירות aveiros by שבת? Shabbat? Right? If I do, for example, I
pluck something and I water something or whatever, you know, they're different
מלאכות, melachot, of the ל"ט מלאכות, lamed tet melachot, and it's two
sin offerings. Okay, let's say, however, I do an אב av and
a תולדה. toldah. So an אב av and a תולדה toldah would
be, I don't know, I water a plant and I also, and
I prune a tree, I prune it for the sake of growth.
Two different types of ways of encouraging, of making the tree grow
better. Okay, so if you do an אב av and a תולדה,
toldah, actually those are both תולדות, toldot, you know, they're both תולדות
toldot of זורע. zoreia. So okay, I plant a seed and I
water a different plant. Okay, I do them both. So is an
אב av and a תולדה, toldah, the watering is a derivative of
the planting of the seed. Is that distinct or are they all
the same category? So רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says that they are,
normally we say they're the same category and you cannot be חייב
chayav for doing an אב av and a תולדה toldah if you,
you know, multiple times. It's all one category, you're only חייב chayav
once. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says no, you can be חייב chayav
the תולדה במקום אב. toldah bimkom av. So if you plant a
seed and water a plant, you're still going to bring two, you're
going to bring two קרבנות, korbanot, okay, if you did it בשוגג.
beshogeg. That's רבי אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer position by שבת. Shabbat. Okay, so
now why is that interesting? Because הא אב ואב בבת אחת, ha
av v'av bat achas, that would imply that if I did the
same אב, av, it's only because it's the אב av and the
תולדה toldah that they're, that I get two, that I bring two
קרבנות. korbanot. But if it's the same אב av twice, if I
basically watered a plant and watered a plant, or plucked an apple
and plucked an apple, פטור, patur, you're exempt, meaning you're not exempt,
but you don't bring two, you only bring one. So you see
it's possible to do two מלאכות melachot and only bring one. And
we don't say, why is that? Why couldn't רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
do... Why would you say it's two separate acts?
Why wouldn't you do a קל וחומר kal vachomer if you're חייב
chayav for two for an אב av and תולדה toladah you'd be
חייב chayav for...
No, oh that's a good point. But the reason אב av and
אב av is not distinct אבות, avot, it's the same אב. av.
So he says the reason you're חייב chayav. two, as we'll see
about that in a second, but presumably, the reason he says אב
av and תולדה toladah you're חייב chayav two is because they have
distinct labels. Planting a seed is distinct from watering. One, you know,
so therefore, but if they're the same label, planting and planting, then
he would say that it's only one. Okay, so you see there
are cases where Rabbi Eliezer would say in two distinct acts, even
if it's planting and planting, it would be only one.
חידוש chiddush by שבת, Shabbat, but he says it by sex.
No, the חידוש chiddush by שבת Shabbat is planting and, it's אב
av and תולדה. toladah. No, so that's exactly proving Rav Yosef's point.
So you see that what he was saying was only by sex,
but by other things you see he would combine them. Yeah, exactly.
So there you see, you see that if it was the same
thing multiple times, it would be only one. ואי אמרת ve-i amart
it's a תנא tanna of Rabbi Eliezer משום דקא עביד תרתי, mishum
de-ka avid tartei, if you think Rabbi Eliezer always says when it's
two acts you always bring two, even the same מלאכה, melachah, אמאי
פטור, amai patur, why are you exempt? So, what, I mean not
exempt, but why is it only one? So אמר מר בריה דרבינא,
amar Mar berei de-Ravina, אנא ורב נחמן בר זכריה תרגימנא הכא. ana
ve-Rav Nachman bar Zechariah targimna hacha. So I and Rav Nachman bar
Zechariah, we explained that the case of doing two of the same
אב av twice is only one מלאכה, melachah, is only one קרבן,
korban, it's the following case. הכא במאי עסקינן, hacha be-mai askinan, בדלית
המודלית על גבי תאנה. be-dalit ha-mudelet al gabi te'enah. You have let's
say a vine that is wrapped around a fig tree or growing
on a trellis and the fig tree is also grown through the
trellis, you see whatever. וקצצן בבת אחת. ve-ketzatzan be-vat achat. You're basically
trying to, you know, cut a fig off. But the only way
you can access to cutting the fig off, or maybe it's not
the only way, but at the same time you figure look, you've
got your vine here and you've got your fig and you want
to do two things. You want to basically say, oh I need
the fig, and I might as well also prune my, you know,
prune my vine while I'm at it. And you cut them both.
Now, if you're pruning your vine for the sake of growth, although
it's being done by cutting, it's not the מלאכה melachah of קוצר.
kotzer. You're not cutting, cutting is for the sake of the produce
that you're trying to, that you're taking away. Actually, it's a מלאכה
melachah of זריעה zeriah because you are encouraging the growth. So that
would be a, that would be two different מלאכות melachot in one
act, right? קוצר kotzer and השקאה hashka'ah or זריעה, zeriah, okay, in
one act. So in that type of a
case, משום הכי מחייב רבי אליעזר הואיל ושמות מוחלקין וגופין מוחלקין. mishum
hachi mechayev Rabbi Eliezer ho'il u-shemot muchlakin ve-gufin muchlakin. In that type
of a case he would say you get two קרבנות. korbanot. Why?
It's two, two different things, it's a fig and a vine, and
it's two different labels, קוצר kotzer and זריעה. zeriah. Okay, דכוותיה, de-chavateih,
now if you had that scenario and it was actually the same
מלאכה, melachah, קצר וקצר, katzar ve-katzar, let's say you actually had I
don't know, two different fig trees, or I don't know, a fig
tree and an apple tree growing right next to each other. And
with one cut of your, what do you call those things, cutters?
What? Scythe, scythe is for wheat, but whatever. With one cut of
the pruning shears, you cut both an apple and a fig. Okay,
but it's both קוצר. kotzer. היכי משכחת לה, heichi mashkachat lah, so
דכוותיה קצר וקצר היכי משכחת לה דמיפטר, de-chavateih katzar ve-katzar heichi mashkachat
lah de-miptar, you'd be exempt for, what, to go? So קצר שתי
גרוגרות בבת אחת. katzar shtei grogerot be-vat achat. Okay, here it actually
has that it was basically, you know, גרוגרות grogerot is just the
size. You cut the two things of the minimum size at the
same
time. אבל קצר כגרוגרת וחזר וקצר כגרוגרת חייב. aval katzar ke-grogeret ve-chazar
ve-katzar ke-grogeret chayav. With separate acts you'd be חייב. So that was
a long way of saying the following. The proof was that Rabbi
Eliezer would say that if it was the same מלאכה melachah twice,
that you only bring only one. So you see, says that even
if you do things twice, if you could conceptually combine them, you're
only going to bring one. And the answer is no, we're not
conceptually combining them, we're really combining them. If you had two, you
were cutting two things at once, and it was let's say again,
you know, again, an apple tree and a fig tree, so it
would be that would be you would say you bring only one
חטאת chatat because it was literally the same act. So that's where
he's saying that if it was two things at once you bring
one. If it's at once. But if you did it sequentially, there
Rava would argue, there Rava would argue that even though it's the
same מלאכה melachah and even though in theory you could combine them,
as long as you haven't combined them, as long as they're distinct
acts, Rabbi Eliezer would say you bring different sin offerings. So just
to summarize this, okay, the basic principles, when do you bring multiple
sin offerings? Different either bodies, גופים מוחלקין, gufim muchlakin, or different labels,
different sins, or you remember in between. Comes along Rabbi Eliezer and
he says you could even bring multiple sin offerings for the same
thing for multiple acts. And then the question is, is he only
saying that by sex where it's impossible to imagine it to have
it taking place at once, or would he say it by all
things? And Rava who says he would say by all things, different
acts is different sin offerings, would the one case he would agree
in the שבת Shabbat scenario we just gave is not when it
was multiple acts, but it was the same act and doing the
same type of sin but with multiple sort of multiple different things,
there he would say it is one. It could be, but the
point then it's questionable if we would call it קוצר וקוצר. kotzer
ve-kotzer. So I was trying to get an example where we would
more obviously call it קוצר וקוצר. kotzer ve-kotzer.
Okay, it's two separate acts, two separate things being done conceptually, but
all done in the same act and all done in the same
time. It wouldn't make a difference, it just makes... Right, it would
be קל וחומר, kal vachomer, but it's a bigger חידוש chiddush when
you say different acts. Exactly, so for example about picking two apples
from the same tree, that's just my question.
If you pick an apple and pick another apple, he would say
it's two separate acts? According to רבה, Rabba, according to רבי אליעזר,
Rabbi Eliezer, you'd be חייב twice, two קרבנות. korbanos. Okay, let's go
on. ועוד שאל, Ve-od sha'al, now we take a complete digression because
we're talking about interesting conversations that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva had when
they were going shopping. It's not clear if this is the same
time or not, but let's take a look. ועוד שאל רבי עקיבא,
Ve-od sha'al Rabbi Akiva, Rabbi Akiva also asked them
the following question: אבר המדולדל בבהמה
מהו? Eiver hameduldal biveheimah mahu? So maybe on the one hand they
were talking about sex because it was about a wedding feast, and
they're also talking about animals because they're in a meat market maybe,
I don't know. So he says, let's say you have a limb
dangling from an animal. Now if a limb falls off an animal
when it's alive, it's אבר מן החי, eiver min hachai, or from
a human being, and it causes טומאה. tumah. Let's say it hasn't
completely detached. Let's say the animal's alive and the limb is dangling.
Is it yet considered an אבר מן החי eiver min hachai to
cause טומאה? tumah? בבהמה מהו, Biveheimah mahu, what's the law? אמרו לו
לא שמענו, Amru lo lo shamanu, we don't have a tradition about
this, אבל שמענו, aval shamanu, we do have a tradition that אבר
המדולדל באדם שהוא טהור, eiver hameduldal be'adam shehu tahor, that if a
limb is dangling from a person, right, it is טהור, tahor, although
once the limb falls off it's אבר מן החי. eiver min hachai.
וכך היו, Vekach hayu, and not only that, this is going to
get a little bit graphic, וכך היו מוכי שחין עושים בירושלים, vekach
hayu mokei shechin osim biyerushalayim,
people that had leprosy, right, which limbs fall off, this is what
they would do
in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. What would they do? Now, ah, you see it's
right around פסח Pesach time, so it's exactly perfect for us. So
a person has this limb dangling, he wants to go ahead and
bring his קרבן פסח. korban Pesach. He doesn't want first of all
to have his limb dangling over פסח, Pesach, and also, also maybe
he doesn't want it to fall off and then he'll become טמא.
tamei. So how is he going to go ahead and take care
of this problem before פסח? Pesach? I mean it's a little disturbing
because he actually realizes that he's not going to be, his limb
is going to be lost to him, and now it's just focusing
on the פסח Pesach aspect. So what does he do? הולך
לו ערב פסח אצל הרופא, Holech lo erev Pesach eitzel harofeh, he
goes ערב פסח erev Pesach to the doctor, וחותכו, vechotcho,
and the doctor cuts the, detaches the limb. Now the doctor won't
cut it all off because then the doctor becomes טמא tamei and
the doctor can't bring his קרבן פסח. korban Pesach. So what he
does is he cuts it עד שמניח בו כשערה, ad shemaniach bo
kisa'arah, and he leaves it dangling like by a thread, by a
thread of skin. So it's, he almost completely severs it. Okay, so
the doctor is טהור tahor because now the doctor, it's not yet
a detached limb. Now how is he going to detach it from
himself without becoming טמא? tamei? So he does is ותוחבו בסירה, vetochvo
besirah, this is like you know how they talked about how you
would yank out a loose tooth, he nails the limb, you know,
with like a nail against a wall or something while it's still
attached to him by a thread, ונמשך ממנו, venimshach mimenu, and he
yanks, and therefore it detaches from him, but he's not touching it,
he's not holding it and pulling it, then he's touching it. Okay,
so he's detaching it from him without touching it, so he's טהור.
tahor. ונמשך ממנו והלה עושה פסחו והרופא עושה פסחו, Venimshach mimenu vehala
oseh pischo veharofeh oseh pischo, they can go and bring their קרבן
פסח. korban Pesach. Again, you know,
it's a little funny that... So here we are, it is a
very disturbing graphic case and all we're worried about is can they
bring their קרבן פסח, korban Pesach, but presumably that's what they were
worried about.
You don't become טמא tamei if you touch it?
Right, because only when it becomes detached is it a source of
טומאה, tumah, and therefore once it's detached he's no longer touching it.
That's exactly the point. So you see until it's detached it's not
טמא. tamei. ורואים אנו שהדברים קל וחומר, Vero'im anu shehadvarim kal vachomer,
and presumably it's a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. If a human limb,
which is a greater source of טומאה, tumah, a human being than
animals as we'll see in the גמרא, Gemara, even that does not
cause טומאה tumah when it's dangling, how much more so would an
animal limb not cause טומאה tumah when it's dangling. Is this שחין
צרעת? shechin tzara'as? Let's take a look. Yeah, but because it's not
biblical צרעת, tzara'as, it's a real medical condition that causes limbs to
fall off.
Is this the מצורע metzora they're talking about?
I don't know if it's the שחין מצרים, shechin mitzrayim, but the
medical condition, the medical condition that causes limbs to fall off is
leprosy, maybe there are others. Let's take a look at the גמרא.
Gemara. תנן התם, Tnan hatam, now what the גמרא's Gemara focus is
not going to be on the קל וחומר kal vachomer and whether
it has to fall off to cause טומאה, tumah, the גמרא's Gemara
question is going to be on why not in the act of
detaching the limb, did that at the same moment that the limb
became detached, don't we say that it essentially was also touching the
person and transmitted the טומאה? tumah? So let's take a look.
You said that with the birth and when that spot where they're
separating...
Exactly, yeah, we had this a couple times, exactly that, at the
moment of separation do you also view it as a type of
a contact? So let's take a look. תנן התם, Tnan hatam, המוחק
את הכרישה, hamochek es hakrisha, somebody is basically crushing a leek which
has absorbed water, like rainwater תוספות Tosafos says, which because it's rainwater
it does not yet have a status of water because liquids only
have a status if you want them, if you desire them, and
this just got soaked with rainwater. So you're crushing this leek, והסוחט
בשערו, vehasocheit bise'aro, or you squeeze out your hair that got wet.
with rain water, or your garment. מה שבתוכו אינה בכי יותן. Mah
shebetokho einah be-ki yutan.
Okay, the water that is absorbed in these things, the rain water,
is not yet considered a liquid to make food susceptible for טומאה
tumah because you have not yet shown that you desire them, they
just got rain water got absorbed. ויוצא ממנו הרי הן בכי יותן.
V'yotzei mimenu harei hein be-ki yutan. And but once you squeeze it
out, then it is בכי יותן, be-ki yutan, it is considered to
be desired. Now why is it desired? You're squeezing it out. So
תוספות Tosafos sort of says, well, because actually the very fact that
you are doing an act with the water and you're removing it,
that gives it some status as a liquid even bracketing the question
of whether you desire it or not. Okay, but that's not our
focus. Our focus is that when they get squeezed out, then they
become considered a liquid to make things susceptible. And now, and אמר
שמואל, Amar Shmuel, דקלחא עצמה הוכשרה. Dekalcha atzmah hukhsharah. So you're squeezing
it out of this of this leek, the liquid that is as
it's coming out is considered liquid, and שמואל Shmuel says because it's
liquid as it's coming out, it makes the leek susceptible for טומאה
tumah because as it's coming out it gets the status of a
liquid to make things susceptible and at that moment it's touching the
leek. So it's a similar analogy, as it's coming out it gets
its status and it affects the thing it's coming out from. Okay,
so גמרא Gemara says מאי טעמא, Mai ta'ama, what's the reason? בשעת
פרישה ממנה הוכשרה, B'sha'as perishah mimena hukhsharah, at the moment that it's
the liquid is coming out of the leek, it makes the leek
susceptible. והתנן, V'hatnan, so you see at the moment of separation it
affects the thing, but how does that work with our משנה? We
taught in our משנה, ערב פסח הלך לו אצל רופא וצערה, Erev
Pesach halakh lo eitzel rofei v'tziarah, and the limb gets yanked off.
ואי אמרת דבשעת פרישתן הוכשרה, V'ee amart d'v'sha'as perishasan hukhsharah, if you
say by liquid when it's separating it makes the leek susceptible, האי
נמי ההוא אבר המדולדל בשעת פרישתו מאדם נטמא לאדם? Hai nami hahu
eivar hameduldal b'sha'as perishaso mei-adam nitma l'adam? How about this dangling limb,
why don't we say at the moment of separation it's considered to
have transfer, you know, that exact moment of separation is also a
moment of contact and why doesn't it make the person טמא? tamei?
So you so what's the difference? So גמרא Gemara says כי דאמר
רב יוסף בניצן בכל כוחן הכא נמי בניצן בכל כוחן. Ki d'amar
Rav Yosef b'nitzin b'khol kokhan hakha nami b'nitzin b'khol kokhan. The difference
is how is it separated. When it's when it's sort of squirts
out powerfully, so then it doesn't linger, the stuff just separates. If
however you're squeezing something out, you imagine liquid slowly, then the liquid
after it separates there's a moment of touch before it falls away.
So if that's true that there's a difference by squeezing out of
the limb, if you like, you know, if you squeeze out powerfully
it just, you know, squirts out and it doesn't touch, then it
would be different. If you squeeze it out slowly, you know, it
sort of it adheres for a second before falling away. Similarly by
the limb, if, you know, you yank off the limb slowly, maybe
at the second of separation you were still touching it. But if
you do a quick yank, then it completely separates, there was no
moment of touch. Okay, והיכא איתמר דרב יוסף, V'heikha itmar d'Rav Yosef,
where was רב יוסף Rav Yosef said, that original statement? אהא, Aha,
on the following statement. זב וטמא מת שהיו מהלכין. Zav v'tamei meis
she-hayu mahalakhin. You have a case of a זב, zav, a male
זב, zav, or somebody that has touched a dead body, so they're
both an אב הטומאה, av hatumah, and they were going on the
road, וירדו עליהן גשמים, v'yardu aleihen geshamim, and it rained on them.
So again, this water does not yet have a status of liquid,
it's rain water that they have not, you know, handled or desired.
אף על פי שסוחטין, Af al pi she-sokhtin,
even though they squeeze, we'll skip the parenthesis, מצד העליון לצד התחתון,
mitzad ha-elyon l'tzad ha-tachton, they squeeze the water from let's say the
top of their garment and it runs down to the bottom of
their garment, טהורין. tehorin. It's still considered טהור, tahor, it's not considered
to be liquid and their touching it doesn't make it טמא. tamei.
שאין מחשבין אלא עד שיצאו מכולן. She-ein machshavin ela ad she-yeitzu mikulan.
It's not considered liquid until it completely gets away from them. It
got absorbed into their clothes, only once it fully separates from their
clothes. If it runs down their clothes to a different part, it's
not yet liquid. יצאו מכולן, Yeitzu mikulan, if it went if it
fully departed from them, from their hair, their clothes and whatever, הרי
מכשירין, harei makhshirin, then it becomes considered a liquid to make other
things susceptible, it becomes a liquid that it itself can become טמא.
tamei. Anyway, that happens at the moment after it separates. Okay, and
we'll read the parenthesis, שאין הוכשר אלא לאחר שיצאו מגופו, she-ein hukhshar
ela l'achar she-yeitzu migupo, only when it separates. So how could that
be? How is that different than the leek case? With the leek
case it's considered to come in contact as it separates. So אמר
רב יוסף בניצן בכל כוחן, Amar Rav Yosef b'nitzin b'khol kokhan, when
they're squirted out powerfully, then the liquid doesn't linger, then it just
separates. When it's squirted out slowly, then it lingers and then it
comes in contact. Okay, so that is that issue about a complete
digression about these things that they were asking in this market. Let's
just read the next משנה, get a little further, we won't do
the גמרא Gemara because that is also one more case about defining
multiple sins or not. ועוד שאלן רבי עקיבא, V'od sha'alan Rabbi Akiva,
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva also asked them, presumably also in the same
case. Now we're going to have the a combination of the two.
It's going to be about animals and about multiple sins. Okay, השוחט
חמישה זבחים בחוץ בהעלם אחת. Ha-shocheit chamishah zevachim bachutz b'he'elam achat. Somebody
שחט shechted five different animals outside of the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash,
five different קרבנות korbanos in one state of forgetfulness. מהו? Mahu? חייב
על כל אחת ואחת או אחת על כולן? Chayav al kol achat
v'achat o achat al kulan? Multiple or one? Now that's exactly the
mirror image of the previous question, right? The previous question was one
person multiple multiple sins, this is multiple animals, different גופים, gufim, but
the same sin. Right, so and presumably we know the answer. The
answer is multiple sin offerings. אמרו לו *Amru lo*, they said to
him, לא שמענו lo shamanu, *lo shama'nu*, we don't know. אמר רבי
יהושע *Amar Rabbi Yehoshua*, but Rabbi Yehoshua said, שמעתי *Shama'ti*, but I
did hear the following thing. באוכל מזבח אחד מחמש תנחויין *Be'ocheil mizevach
echad meichamesh tanchuyin*, and this is a Rabbi Yehoshua we quoted before,
not a case of slaughtering animals, but a case of eating. That
if somebody ate from one sacrifice that from five different pots and
we'll describe later what five different pots is, but let's say prepared
five different ways, בהעלם אחד *be'helem echad*, in one state of forgetfulness,
and this would be a case let's say before the blood was
sprinkled, so it would be מעילה Meilah *me'ilah*, misuse of קרבנות Korbanot,
*korbanot*, because the blood was not sprinkled yet, שהוא חייב על כל
אחת ואחת משום מעילה Meilah. *shehu chayav al kol achat ve'achat mishum
me'ilah*, that you bring multiple. Now that is radical, right? It's the
same sin, the same animal, the only thing that makes it different
is that it was prepared in five different pots, in five different
ways. So if that's enough to say multiple sin offerings, the same
sin, the same animal, five different pots, רואה אני שהדברים קל וחומר
*ro'eh ani shehadvarim kal vachomer*, I could make a קל וחומר *kal
vachomer*, that if you can do that multiple sins, how much more
so if you do five different animals and you shecht them outside
the בית המקדש *Beit HaMikdash*, would it be five sin offerings?
But isn't the answer Rabbah, ה' נשי נדה וחמש *hey nashi niddah
ve'chamesh*? Right.
So the point here is, yes. So Michael is saying, isn't this
exactly the case of גופי מחלקין *gufei muchlakin*? And the point and
the answer to that is the following is, to some degree what
this question is, is how do you define גופי מחלקין *gufei muchlakin*?
When there are different people involved, clearly there are different acts. Man
sleeping with different women, there are different people involved, different acts. But
here, they're all animals, meat, right? So if I, for example, let
me give you a simple example, Michael, why don't I say if
I ate this כזית *kezayit* of חלב *cheilev* and an hour later
ate that כזית *kezayit* of חלב *cheilev*, why don't I say גופי
מחלקין *gufei muchlakin*? That was one כזית *kezayit*, that's a different כזית
*kezayit*. Let's say that כזית *kezayit* of חלב *cheilev* came from one
animal, that כזית *kezayit* came from another animal. Would I say גופי
מחלקין *gufei muchlakin* or would I say no, it's all fat? So
that is exactly the question. When it's about people, men and women
having sex, clearly it's a different act. When it's about objects, like
one piece of חזיר *chazir* and another piece of חזיר *chazir*, we
don't call it גופי מחלקין *gufei muchlakin*. We call it the same
act multiple times. So what about when it's five animals? They're not
just pieces of meat, it's five animals. So he says, well, how
about if it's different meat prepared in different pots? If that's different,
then certainly five animals should be different. But this is exactly the
question, how do you define גופי מחלקין *gufei muchlakin* when you move
from people to animals to meat? Okay, so he said, look, meat
can sometimes be five different things.
Five different pots in five different ways?
Well, that the גמרא *Gemara* will discuss that. Okay, so that was
his first answer. רואה אני שהדברים קל וחומר *Ro'eh ani shehadvarim kal
vachomer*. אמר רבי שמעון *Amar Rabbi Shimon*, לא כך שאל רבי עקיבא
*lo kashal Rabbi Akiva*. That wasn't Rabbi Akiva's question, because that was
comparing the case of slaughtering to eating and maybe they're different. It
was really an eating question. It was comparing eating to eating. אלא
באוכל נותר Nosar מחמשה זבחים בהעלם אחד *Ela be'ocheil notar mechamesh zevachim
be'helem echad*. You ate נותר Nosar *notar*, like leftover meat from a
sacrifice, from five different sacrifices. מהו *Mahu*? חייב אחת על כולן *Chayav
achat al kulan*, is it one sin offering because it's five different
sacrifices, like the case of five different forbidden acts of sex? Right,
five, I mean, five different women. או חייב על כל אחת ואחת
*O chayav al kol achat ve'achat*? Or would it be, I'm sorry,
is it one or is it multiple or is it distinct? And
exactly that's the question, is that גופי מחלקין *gufei muchlakin*, five different
sacrifices, right? Or in the end of the day, it's meat and
we don't consider that different acts, we consider that the same act
multiple times. So essentially this is a question of how do you
define גופי מחלקין *gufei muchlakin* when you move from people to animals
to meat? That was his question. אמרו לו *Amru lo*, they said
to him, לא שמענו lo shamanu. *lo shama'nu*, we don't have a
tradition about this. אמר רבי יהושע *Amar Rabbi Yehoshua*, said Rabbi Yehoshua,
שמעתי *Shama'ti*, I did hear, באוכל מזבח אחד מחמש תנחויין בהעלם אחד
*be'ocheil mizevach echad meichamesh tanchuyin be'helem echad*, and this is where it's
relevant because it's eating to eating, that if you ate from an
animal that the blood hasn't been sprinkled, so it's מעילה Meilah *me'ilah*,
even if it's one sacrifice but five different pots, שהוא חייב על
כל אחת ואחת משום מעילה Meilah *shehu chayav al kol achat ve'achat
mishum me'ilah*. ורואה אני שהדברים קל וחומר *Ve'ro'eh ani shehadvarim kal vachomer*.
And for God's sake, if the same sacrifice prepared five different ways
is five different acts, how much more so is it if it's
נותר *notar* from five different animals? אמר לו רבי עקיבא *Amar lo
Rabbi Akiva*, Rabbi Akiva responded, אם הלכה נקבל *im halacha nekabel*. Look,
if you have a tradition, then I'll accept it about my case.
אם לדין *Im ledin*, but if you want to discuss it logically,
יש תשובה *yesh teshuvah*. Then I can have a response to you.
Your example of מעילה Meilah *me'ilah* prepared five different ways is not
relevant to my example of נותר *notar*. If you focus just physically,
you're right. My thing is more physically distinct, five sacrifices, yours is
one sacrifice five ways. But there's also a difference of the nature
of the sin. You had an example of מעילה *me'ilah* and I'm
talking about נותר *notar*. Why is it different? אמרו לו השב *Amru
lo hashev*, said let me hear your response. אמר *Amar*, he said,
לא אם אמרת במעילה שעשה בה המאכיל כאוכל והמהנה כנהנה v'hamahane k'nehane.
*lo im amarta bime'ilah she'asah ba hamachil ke'ocheil ve'hamahaneh keneheneh*. מעילה *Me'ilah*
has in your case where it's מעילה *me'ilah* done five different ways,
five different pots, מעילה *me'ilah* has other stringencies. Maybe therefore we would
consider it multiple sins, multiple sin offerings. What are the stringencies of
מעילה? Number one, עושה המאכל כאוכל. oseh ham'achal k'ochel. If I feed
you
קרבנות, Korbanot, forbidden קרבנות, and you are the one eating it, nevertheless
I'm the one doing מעילה because I'm the one that initially misused
the object by giving it to you to eat. So even the
feeder is treated like the one who eats. That's a stringency. Number
one, והמהנה כנהנה. Let's say it's not about eating. Let's say it's
about I gave it to you to put on as oil, to
anoint, and you did it. The fact that I took it out
of הקדש Hekdesh by giving it to you makes me as bad
as the one who did it. So those are stringencies by מעילה.
Not only that, צירוף אצל מעילה לזמן מרובה. tziruf etzel Meilah lizman
merubeh. Right, when it comes to eating, normally you have to eat
what did we say before? כזית בכדי אכילת פרס. kezayit bichdei achilat
pras. But let's say by מעילה I benefited a little bit today
and a little bit of five hours from now and a little
bit more five hours from now, that would all combine because it's
not so much about eating, it's more about deriving benefit and misuse.
So מעילה has a lot of stringencies. So because מעילה has a
lot of stringencies, I could say the same animal prepared five ways
is considered five sins. But תאמר בנותר שאין בו אחת מאלו? tomar
biNosar she'ein bo achat me'elu? נותר has none of those stringencies. So
maybe נותר from five different animals is still considered one sin multiple
times and one sin offering. I wanted to say two things to
summarize this. So again to repeat conceptually, we've already laid out the
idea that גופין מחולקין gufin m'chulakim is different sin offerings, שמות מחולקין
shemot m'chulakim is different, but here the question is what does גופין
מחולקין gufin m'chulakim mean? If it's different people, so you know, different
people are involved in the act, that makes it a different act
and different sins. So you know, a man with different women is
different acts. But here we're saying let's say it's you know this
piece of meat and that piece of meat, this קרבן korban and
that קרבן, korban, this animal and that animal. Is that different acts
or in the end it's the same act multiple times because you're
not dealing with people, you're dealing more with objects and animals and
maybe that's all the same act. So that's the question of how
do you define the parameters of גופין מחולקין. gufin m'chulakim. And that's
summarizing and one other important point just to notice. Notice that Rabbi
Akiva is asking a question and the answers are לא שמענו, shamanu,
שמענו, לא שמענו. Can we compare it to this? And he said,
oh you know if you have a tradition fine, but you want
to discuss it logically here's what I have to say. This once
again highlights you know the way in which Rabbi Akiva was the
major break, I mean he wasn't the only one, but from what
came before him and from the idea that everything is based on
tradition. Right, I mean in a way so you know there's two
trends in תורה שבעל פה. Torah Shebe'al Peh. One is just מסורה
mesorah and passing down and the other is using your own intellect
and creativity and so on. So he's asking these, he's having a
fun, a fun you know trying to think of these theoretical, they're
not giving him a direct answer, they're just saying oh we didn't
have a tradition, we have a tradition, we don't have a tradition.
He wants to talk about the ideas. You know he wants to
be more independently creative about this and that really represents the two
trends within תורה שבעל פה. Torah Shebe'al Peh. Okay.